so uh hi welcome everyone welcome to this magnet
seminar uh today we are really excited and happy
to have this peanut condo Pulu from the Aristotle
University of thessalonic in Greece presenting a
talk entitled archomagnetic research Through The
Eyes of a parliament magnetist a potential impact
of on a study of baked Clays in various geological
environment in Greece um please the spinner go
ahead and with your token the floor is yours thank
you and I thank you Anita and hello to everybody
um today's seminar gives me the opportunity to
present a brief overview of the accumagnetic data
obtained in Greece during the last approximately
25 years by Greek and or foreign research groups
assuming that the discipline is familiar to
the audience I skip all the introduction the
usual introduction and give some key points in
order to enter the main presentation so you all
probably know that the suitable material which
we use in accumagnetism both in situ and moving
I mean portable are the killings the fired
walls and pottery and also ceramic Styles
and other items made of based clay though the
pre-selection of material is now being more and
more detailed and careful uh successful results
are not always obtained and this holds mostly
for the actual intensity ones there are some
prerequisites and gravitations for optimal
results I also go through this very quickly
the abundance of magnetic particles in the
material homogeneous material to be a selected
preferably heating up to high temperatures and
of course volume various environmental
factors which may affect the material
uh in this slide I present a broadly known
in by archaeologists and archaeometrists
so there are studies of archometry involved
involved here about the temperatures reached
within an updraft killing circular one and the
rectangularities these are the most familiar
the most usual findings in excavated killings
in Greece you will notice that the distribution
of temperatures is more homogeneous in the
updraft ones and the more scattered in the
orthogonal killings starting from very
low values 450 enriching approximately
1000 Celsius so a sampling within such Akin has
to take into consideration all these variations
uh the potential duration of a killings building
material is closely related to the geological
environment as killings are basically built with
Clays in very close neighborhood people who did
not travel like kilometers and kilometers to bring
a clay for constructing a killing for pottery and
assemblage of various Clays is uh required and
these can be collected in into within considerable
distances so cannot be representative of the
geology of the area but this has some exceptions
as well which I will present later and we'll
also have an intermediate class of materials
in the broadly known name of Ceramics like tiles
bricks pipes Etc there are some basic experiments
of magnetic meteorology to conduct in a democratic
study and I don't speak about the more elaborated
ones which become more and more numerous I just
limit to the basic ones because this can be useful
later as I hope to show you um the most important
uh factor in the study of bait plays the first
one is the susceptibility since it shows how the
magnetic enhancement of Hyatt Place can progress
and this is monitored to what uh versus uh thermal
um versus temperature and all related to the
geological context of each side a second group of
measurements relies on the thermometeric analysis
and the relevant tests that is the isothermal
remnants so by thermomagnetic analysis you can
see if we detect hematite we have an advanced
oxidation and some grain size distribution while
the isothermal remnants shows us the main carriers
of the magnetization uh in the early 2000 uh
the study of the role plays was initiated in
Bulgaria and this um I could say Innovative
work by Jordana vital was followed by others
from Costa Deen of abramov and kovachova
2013-15 now several offers include information
about the Clays used for the fire items mostly
kills during an argumentative study and I cite
very briefly the last uh used and known to us
um having accumulated quite a lot of experience
on sampling these structures so mostly teams
but also fired walls in Greece we developed
a new approach thinking that and observing
that all the above experiments that is the
simple ones I mentioned are traditionally
conducted within the frame of a classic value
magnetic study that is on geological formations
so in the following uh I will first
cite the actual state of the art
what your magnetism in Greece nowadays to give
you an idea though there were some preliminary
data accumulated until 1995 [Music] the real start
and kickoff of archomagnetism was done at the end
of the 90s and mostly through the project
of our the archaeological electromagnetic
applications for cultural heritage then I
will display the geographic distribution of
the studied five structure versus the geological
formations and then we combine with distribution
of polar magnetic results now the database
of directional data from Greece was built
as a whole around the 2014 by the marquetal
but using data until 2010 this compilation
for which I just have one word to tell you
more is the total absence of results through
all the islands of Eastern Aegean which provided
lots lots of pottery and aphorus known to have
traveled towards Sicily to want the Black Sea and
there were reports of excavated kills which never
survived because these islands are very touristic
and excavations never followed the let's say
the legal rule so everything disappeared this
this compilation gave rise to the first secular
variation guys for Greece for directions which you
can see here by the same publication and in this
um uh in these curves Observer uh problems and
I'm I mean empty places for the the prehistoric
periods this part which corresponds to the Dark
Ages is also only calculating but not really
um Based on data and surprisingly this part
corresponding to The Late Late Roman early
Byzantine I mean post-roman let's say mostly
period which is very well covered by structures
in Greece was almost totally unexploited for
this reason we worked on the last 2000 years
by sampling ourselves but also accumulating
the high quality results which were available
in the bibliography and there were new cars um
covering this part I have to well it's written
this is based on Lanos technique but the new
curves are published in 2021 are based in a new
technique ability who is going to present it in a
separate paper and with together with Elena dona
now the same distribution holds for intensities
where we have four times more data as it is
understandable and here we plot the location
of sampling not fabrication which is very
often different but of course it was not easy
to plot also the fabrication side this was also
compiled by the Marco Hotel 2008 and gave rise
to this curve also built with Lanos method but
since then of course many data points were
acquired after 2008 which are here plotted
in red stars and and dots and the other being
continuously completed with uh the last well
you can hear see them hear the Publications
which gave these results and the brand new
one which is now online and pepe covering the
Bronze Age this period of the Bronze Age foreign
with the Spanish team of Madrid uh mostly
for Rivero montero's uh pesis which was
um defended last year on the part of the
magnetic field anomalies around the place
where we expected to find at the time uh the Elia
the container nature normally so we focused to
1600 BC until 180 and this the this compilation
and this work was also done for Italy but here
I present only the Greek data and you can see
how we managed to elaborate uh this oh sorry
uh this uh anomaly and also do a new curve uh
which you can see here for this time period so
we complete by pieces I hope that one day um
somebody not me because I retired will build
the new Carver for this as a whole um schematic
distribution of excavated jeans in Greece they
are in a database a variable online which
I can send to everybody who is interested
different colors represent different
archaeological periods just to give you
an idea because uh these dots correspond
often to workshops and not only one kill
um this work started in 2002 by Elena hasaki now
professor at Tucson Arizona who counted at that up
to that moment 567 excavated kills by now I think
they have past the 700 maybe all over the country
uh following this we plotted by red dots they
are a bit small but I hope that you can see
them uh inside the value this is the geological
map of Greece Greece is geologically a very very
complicated area I have to underline this because
clearly everybody is not familiar with the geology
of Greece which represent everything you can
imagine Alpha informations prayer information
postal informations and so it is becoming a
real um uh let's say challenge to try to combine
structures and ecological
structures with the geology
so here you see the distribution
of excavated killings within the
geological zones of Greece and in order to
make this a figure clearer we represent it
um in this spy diagram if I can say that where you
see that alluvial deposits at the 61 percent are
are surrounding the excavated Kings a second
coming the grace and the granitic Rocks broadly
20 this both these give us complications which I
will try to monitor later the same holds for the
intensities uh you can see the black dots here and
also here uh you should not be surprised by the
fact that everything everything is concentrated
in north and Central Greece it's because a lab is
here and we had access to mostly the informations
in northern Greece mostly for intensities because
all that data I have shown to you before come
for the directions uh do not yield always uh
measurements or results for intensities due to
lack of experiments so here we have about 50
percent alluvial deposits a lot of metamorphic
rocks and limestones let's say coming second
in the same map we have plotted the palomagnetic
data obtained in Greece there is a huge
polymagnetic database which was built uh I
think three years or four years ago through
a project the helpers project and of course uh
encompasses all the results obtained in degrees
by several teams Dutch French British
sometime and Italian I think recently
um so what you see here these dots are areas where
we have value magnetic and because we don't care
about tectonic implications but we do care about
the rock magnetism of the static formations so all
these blue points are the polymagnetic data
and the yellow triangles are the excavated
Kings uh in all periods for historic geometric
classical and Hellenistic I guess Roman as well
so in this in this map there is uh an obvious
wide distribution of polymagnetic data in Greece
and we have a an important and clear information
about the initial geological formations and their
magnetic potential so I selected few examples uh
from different geological zones and archaeological
periods to document this approach um these four
sides come from the peninsula of I have Maps so I
just give you the first idea the peninsula for
Khalid Olympiad and sunny this is in Central
Greece teslie and this is Thessaloniki within
the city this is archomagnetic acche magnetism
part is successful for two out of five killings
Sunny successful for three out of three two out
of two and successful for three out of three but
an additional data set of seven other study skills
within Thessaloniki was used also for comparison
every one of these killing was successful
uh the basic experiments which uh we explore where
the you know the Lowry experiment thermomagnetic
analysis irm again and again so in all these
sites we have several examples of rock magnetism
quite thoroughly examined step by step let's go
first to the study side of olympiada which is in
the beginning of the month after the monastic area
of Mount tapos we have some the five Pottery games
or fairly Hellenistic period that is after
the death of Alexander the Great that is the
Hellenistic period uh you can see the Kings
uh one two three four and there were two
here so five Kings as a whole to as I said
before two out of five were successful only
and why how can we possibly explain this
well this is a geological map of the area
the geological setting comprises granite and
civilized glass and some like Australian and
Marine sediments the poliomagnetism are done on
rocks from the broader study area or was already
published by westfalent authors in 1991. these
polymagnetic results were obtained in sentiments
and volcanics and they were unable to provide
any reliable Direction the archomagnetic results
um though promising in the beginning they
show reversibility one magnetic phase but
only two out of five Kings were providing reliable
results so this is not really very important it's
because we started also RPD and petrography
Etc the atmosphere of firing is you probably
remember for orthogonal kills lies between
these values and so is extremely variable
we moved to Sunny which is the other finger of
calcific peninsula the early Byzantine settlement
of with five things but only three were sampled
they had approximately these feature and they all
worked perfectly here is the geological mostly
sedimentary energy and sediments and including
red Mars which are really prominent in the area
and everything is red and alluvial deposits the
polar magnetism of the Rocks while uh while
it was thoroughly studied um did not uh was
not published for several reasons by the study was
done by uh scholgar marriage and myself so all the
the all the data are shown here the polymagnetic
data quite promising unfortunately not published
monitoring of sustainability was temperature than
not so significant changes and so on and here we
calculated but I'm indirectly with a based on the
geography the temperature distribution uh was the
same as previously we moved southwards to thessali
to a Neolithic side you see 5400 efforts 4600 and
where two file structures uh this is a geology I
mean the the reasoning is the same of your light
limestones and also flip your legacy in deposits
and lots of alluvial there are lots of rivers here
the polar magnetism of the Rocks also published
in 1997 was very successful for the lovers but not
at all for the sad demands which probably gave
rise to the pottery which was also I forgot to
tell you that Pottery was also collected here and
was disastrous no one not a single one reliable
that could be obtained out of 40 fragments uh the
temperature yes the temperatures were calculated
between 600 and 900 so it was quite good for
for um our experiments but the atmosphere was
a reduction reduction redox and the short firing
duration so this probably affected the ceramics
and coming to the last example but the most rich
I think is within the city of Thessaloniki were
three kings were excavated during a Metro
excavation for building new station close
to the railway station you see the three genes uh
around this is ottoman around 1500 A.D and around
40 and samples separately oriented published
in 2021 but in Thessaloniki previously there
were studies as I told you on another seven
Kings within the city within the same central
western part of the city and by Evans and myself
with spataras and all these skills gave reliable
results here represent to you the geological
setting of the area quaternally prove your
like Australian sediments red clay is also very
prominent the palomagnet is more rocks from the
broader study area published in 92 9 2000 um was
done on major reformations along the axios river
which is a sorry running here and which
has provided all the sediments on which
thessalonic is built I mean above
the Bedrock which is a sister mostly
um so their geomagnetic results from all
published annual data explain very very
well why we have reliable directions and there
you can see a drill with a geological section
and displaying very well the red clay series which
are responsible for most of our constructions
all this is about games but I would like
to tell you a few words about Pottery as
I said before Pottery collections are more
complicated but often we have the provenance
within a reasonable distance from the place
of Ray firing either because it is coarse
Pottery or because it is an old one I mean
prehistoric but not a Bronze Age but earlier
Neolithic and this in these periods people were
limited to their let's say easy access areas
so in that cases we can consider that this Pottery
for which I also have 200 there are several
archaeological energy metric studies come from the
same geological formations then we can assume that
the similar examination of the raw materials as
above can be justified we have two examples to
show you the island of fasos North Indian and
the site opposite opposite the Continental side
um I go next and then I come back
so I talk about this area okay here
so the other sides were here here
here and the salons now moving here
these uh these areas are situated within
the crystalline metamorphic Rod of massive
uh the archomagnetic studies in both areas
proved to yield partly satisfying results
from fossils Bronze Age collections that is
five to six fragments were successful out of 36
sampled and studied but failed completely for
three collections of Neolithic Pottery covering
the whole fifth Millennium for the kilitash that
is a total of 45 fragments a whole Millennium and
we were really hoping to obtain data from this
collection which remains of course unpublished
a few small parties published by panzaita so
with the experience acquired now I would say
because several of these samplings I mean the the
kills were sampling the 15 and apart the Thessalon
each part the other teams were some to 10 and
15 years ago with the accumulated experience I
would look more carefully to the geological maps
of the area before sampling because you all know
how painful it can be to try to obtain results
and do measurements and measurements and end
with zero now the failed experiment for example
for degree does is this one this is the material
and this is a very well known and it obtained a
French price of uh Chino Del duka institution uh
it's a really huge excavation you see that the
pre-selection was fine all the subs were like
that it's not a good example I'm choosing um the
three axes gave good information but their eyes
are disastrous and all it all went along like
that so to conclude Greece is spread with a
great amount of archaeological fines and they are
everywhere there are exceptionally well studied
ceramic Collections and pottery Collections and it
would be ableist to better explode this potential
now uh about among the various approaches I know
that there are approaches suggested worldwide but
what we propose here is simpler to look let's say
more carefully to the geology and to try to see if
there are polymagnetic data around which they
are most often and use this database properly
in order to limit let's say the failure of an
archomagnetic study I want to make clear that
we cannot and certainly we not select killings on
the buses of this but we could try to reduce the
failure eliminate not promising candidates
for instance I would not sample on Bianca
uh the five things I have shown to you because
this they belong to a historical period in which
we have plenty plenty of uh constructions the
Hellenistic period is extremely well documented
English it's not something rare and the time it
took us to study among mostly emanuela De Marco
who used these samples for her face is she lost a
lot of time it would not be a wise thing to do and
to complete our um let's say our approach we are
working more with um geologists and meteorologists
in the last years in order to help the evolution
of our geomagnetic studies and here I have to also
say once more I retired two years ago I hope to
be able to help in the lab but my colleague Alina
is taking the float and she already took it some
years ago so I can only hope that she will go on
that's all I thank you for uh oh yes before I
finish there are a few people I want to thank
um Greek archaeologist as a whole uh support and
encouraged us the efforts that are the local uh
um governmental directions in North Greece have
supported our work as well as Delphi halkis and
the cycladic islands and also our department
the French School in Athens and the Easter
Center for both financial and scientific
assistance in the last years thank you
thank you very much and so for the audience now
there is space for questions if you have any
you can receive your hand or you can
use the charts to write your questions
uh Gunther you have a question
hello can you hear me yes I can hear you
hi very nice talk thank you I really
enjoyed your presentation thank you and I
I am aware that the in terms of the archaeological
artifacts that you described these films there was
also a lot of volcanic eruptions to produce a lot
of tethra yes and I wonder if there is any kind of
a like a matching matching approach that you would
you know try to figure out the trm of the tephras
that are fairly well known or somewhat known
when they deposit it along with those archeologic
artifacts from the Kilns and pottery um may I
answer uh this this work could be done only in
one place in Greece in Santorini uh you know the
eruptive island of Santorini there there were yes
uh detailed studies on Lovers by Donald Darling by
Bill dhoni to my knowledge no one else and there
were also um data from Pottery no from kills
sorry but to my knowledge there was no effort
to combine as you say I mean and you keep in mind
that these studies were quite old I mean the 80s
early 90s so yes it is this something which
could be done but has not been done up to now
thank you very much again I really like your talk
and I'm happy that you work really happy thank you
thank you yeah we all enjoyed your talk to
Spina thank you very much well that makes me
less anxious thanks a lot you really did a lot of
work in all these years that so it's gonna be a
legacy yes I hope uh I hope to be able to continue
for a while because I really like this discipline
I really do thank you um is there
another question from the audience
oh okay let's let's give Kathy
that a priority Commerce yes please
hello it's lovely lovely to see you and
really nice it's so nice to hear all of
that work come together lovely I'm very
happy that they mentioned the art project
no it's it's really nice to see as say the
legacy of it all and what I was wondering
is is there a prospect of going back
to some of the samples where you have
directional data and now doing intensity
measurements and what's the the relative
um merits of doing the intensity measurements
on ceramics as opposed to fired structures
um well we do I mean the leader has set up uh
the Italian experiment in our lab so there are
uh there is work coming out as Publications on
intensities only the big problem is that we have
difficulties to find the structure in situ and we
were really very very lucky to have found all the
structures which were included in emmanuela's
thesis and because there are no public works
that's very simple or if there are there was
for example a pipe installation in northern
Greece and everything was uh let's say buried
in order to keep it for the next Generations
so we have difficulties we try we have very good
connections with their geological community in the
Departments and the efforts um of course we want
to do this but I don't want to speak uh for Elena
because she has maybe to to reply to that uh we do
our best through what we can find and and can you
can you look back at earlier samples uh so
to re-measure but to measure this time the
intensity oh no we don't have access I mean you
know when when we started to really work on that
your magnetism in our lab um everything was
measured for both intensity and directions and
we don't have all all the samples we have samples
which we have not measured yet but they come from
our collections the last five six seven years no
we don't have early samples unfortunately yes okay
we don't it's good yeah but it's a great it's so
nice to see it together so nice to see you Kathy
thank you um Gunther at the
second question please go ahead
okay can you hear me yes and I can hear and I
can see you now that's better okay um I you have
indicated that the Greece has a lot of complex
geology as you showed in the map and uh and then
I got the feeling that somehow it was reflected
by by the magnetic data that you had meaning
that there was probably different rocks that were
available for the Kiln so what was the what was
the relationship between the very complex geology
and the Magnetic data that you have discussed
um well I'll try to answer to my best because
when we did all the paleomagnetic sampling
which started in the late 80s in Greece of course
there was nothing to do with archomagnetism but uh
well I have to start in a different way the
target of the magnetic measurements increased
at that time was mostly tectonic I mean we needed
to um to document rotations and as a second step
by different teams mandatory stratigraphy and
this was an overall Target not only our lab
but also a big projects from other labs for
example Netherlands and the France the event
lab and Utrecht lab and also uh uh Great
Britain I mean Tony Morris work so this all
I had to do with geodynamics but Within These
studies there is a included a precious database
of rock magnetic information so according to
where our teams are which we now know but of
course we did not know if that period we try
to see if the sampling we did because as you
understand we do not sample metamorphic rocks we
sampled the sediments with some lavas and partly
granites so there if there are connections of the
magnetic properties on both that is the target
I don't know if I answered well you you always
answer well and I have a follow-up question uh
because of the very contrasting geology I would
assume that there is also um kind of like a map
of magnetic anomalies of Greece which means that
some areas would have a much larger magnetic field
compared to the other yeah and if you if you if
you took it into account when you were trying
to make some kind of a geomagnetic not we did
not no because this cannot be combined and then
positive on that we have Maps uh and we had a very
performant team of uh applied geophysics we have
modelings of the geomagnetic field but this is
a modeled uh according to days to daily yearly
um variations so this could influence the magnetic
refraction maybe maybe but it doesn't play any
important role on the magnetism which is recorded
or in the Rocks no it doesn't it doesn't affect
well thank you very much something else you
can email me if you want something I can give
and give you some information you can email
me well you will have said during your talk
that you would make available some of
the database to anyone who is interested
so I would be the one interested
okay thank you Anita I think it's
you now yes um well I want to agree
priority to anybody else who has a question
um but I guess my question was um regarding
so they killed and the Ceramics so uh the
provenance of the tsunamis could be different so
perhaps uh they would of course give only poll
intensity data but maybe um more reliable
do you see this in in in in your results
um we have a few examples where we uh obtained
the data from both skills and the production okay
in in what I have shown you we only have this in
one Kiln in Thessaloniki there are other cases for
example uh Paris Island in the cycladic complex
where we had both the kill and the Ceramics in
Thessaloniki um they were both working very well
and we know that the Ceramics were local by the
archaeologists and also by the fact that they were
used for domestic use so in that cases you don't
search for elaborate you know constructions in
Paris Island the Paris Island is the first uh if
you want to if you go back to the presentation
the front slide shows the Manuela sampling uh
the Paris Island cleans on the right top the
pottery worked better than the Kings because
there is an explanation of course because the
kill is well built without a launched everything
limestones which we did not know and we moved
to the cycladic islands the whole team myself
to sample with the archaeologists who had
excavated and what she forgot to tell us
that this was mostly limestone so imagine
that we have to do a lot of work to try to
sample the the Clays which were Incorporated
within the limestone so only two out of five
getting to work but the battery was absolutely
fine it was published by and called force in 2012.
thank you very much
so I would like to thank everybody for joining
um uh to the seminars this year uh 22 was a great
year um we hope to continue next year we have
already Helen up of speakers but we are still
looking for more speakers and so you're welcome
to contact anyone of the team and would like to
remind you that previous talks are public
available on YouTube and you're welcome to
um to follow our YouTube channel and like it and
watch it every watch as much you want
and thanks again and we would like to
um to wish you the best for this year
and see you next year thank you very much